Hi, welcome back to our at-home retreat.
I'd like to thank Stanley Chen for
coming to translate. He and Alison have
been working very hard, and thank you for
that. Session 19, we call it "One Wheel,
Three Lives." And the picture you see
here is of three sets of twelve
links, like in three wheels. And the image
I want you to have in your mind, is the
links of the first wheel start to turn,
and then before it finishes, it triggers
another wheel, and then before that
finishes, it triggers another wheel. So
before the first wheel is finished,
there's a second wheel started. And is it
possible a third wheel starts? Because if
that's true, the things we do in one day,
they might interact for thousands of
lives. We could be creating thousands of
lives in one day.
Then don't forget what our big job is in
the lam rim (LAM RIM), in this middle
motivation person--they're trying to
reach Nirvana, just for themselves.
They're trying to stop the Wheel of Life,
which also you can call "wheel of
pain." It's not a wheel of life; it's a
wheel of pain. So it's okay if you want to
think of one wheel with twelve parts, and
you have to stop it. You can think like
that. But at some point, you're going to
have to realize that in one day you are
triggering hundreds of thousands of
wheels--lifetimes. But there are also many
wheels going on. Like the wife in the
kitchen,
last week she yelled at her kids. She
started a mini wheel going. She did
link one, and two, and half of three--and
then that triggered things in the
kitchen, three or four days later. The
husband yelled at her before she had
a chance to talk. Then she says, "He yells
at me. I didn't even say anything yet!"
Then she yells back. And it's amazing
that in, I don't know, a hundred thousand
years people didn't figure it out. They
didn't figure out that the husband is
yelling because the you yelled at your kids last week. And
they didn't figure out that if you yell
at your husband, then the kids are going to
be bad next week. Then you're gonna yell
at your kids again. See, you get this
feeling that multiple wheels are being set in
motion. In the example we just gave, there's
three lifetimes already. Kids bedroom, Friday
night. Kitchen the next Wednesday. Kids
bedroom next ... the week after that.
Wheels within wheels. So this ...
today's discussion, session 19, let's look
at three lifetimes in a single set of
twelve links. We're not going to call it one wheel, maybe.
de na le chig gi wang du chepay tendrel cha tsang...
(DES NA LAS GCIG GI DBANG DU BYAS PA'I RTEN CHA TSANG...)
...chig tse chig la dzok mi si
(...GCIG TSE GCIG LA RDZOGS MI SRID)
Here's a
very, I don't know, controversial
statement. If you're talking with
reference to--wang du che (DBANG DU BYAS)--if you're talking
with reference to one karmic seed, then it's
impossible for a whole wheel to finish
in one life. We'd like to think one wheel
is one life, but it's actually impossible
to finish a whole wheel in one life. If you didn't
get that right away, then just think
about it. I mean sometimes you should
stop listening to the video, go sit on
your couch, and just think about it for
ten minutes. In a traditional Buddhist class in
the monastery, you're absolutely not
allowed to drink anything, obviously not
allowed to eat anything, not allowed to
go peepee even. Sometimes the class is three
hours! And this video system is so cool
for you.
I mean you can even sit on a toilet and
watch this, and eat pizza at the same
time. Okay, so I don't recommend. Okay
gyog kyang tse nyi ni ngepar gu la
(MGYOGS KYANG TSE GNYIS NI NGES PAR DGOS LA)
So therefore, logically, we just found out
that even at the fastest, it's going to
take two lives to make the seed, water
the seed, and have the seed open into a
life. So just get in this mood of a
seed is planted, and then there's another
series of events which make it ready to
open--which water it. And then, thirdly, it
opens into, for example, a new life.
yang le la... (YANG LAS LA...)
...se len gyi su tab...
(...SRED LEN GYIS GSOS BTAB...)
...ma nupar gyang na
(...MA NUS PAR 'GYANGS NA)
Now what happens if the
seed doesn't get water or fertilizer? And
I'm trying to remember the name of that
Siberian plant, but it's ... I'll give it to
you tomorrow.
But what if that seed drops into a
glacier and it doesn't get real water or
sunlight for thirty-one thousand years?
What happens then?
Okay, so he gives he gives a... what do
call it? A scenario.
pen je kyi yenlak sum...
('PHEN BYED KYI YAN LAG GSUM...)
...tse chig la
(...TSE GCIG LA)
The throwing links--the misunderstanding your husband. Talking,
saying something bad to him, and planting
the seed on your mind. Let's say those
are finished in the first life, then it
doesn't happen that those seeds get
water or fertilizer before that lady
dies. What if she dies, I don't know, that
night? Then she's going to be carrying seeds
to her next life, and then they're going to
have to be watered in the second life. We
call the factory seeds, right? Really they
prepare the seed for opening, like
building a new car.
So she planted the seed in the first
life, she died suddenly. In the second
life, they got water and fertilizer,
because that mind which went into the
second life was still misunderstanding
her bad seeds, which is the best water to
make them strong. So, suppose those seeds
get water, but then she dies again
suddenly, before they can open. Then they
will open in the third life. Okay? Those
four seeds in the middle--four, five,
six, and seven--
body and mind in the womb,
sense organs developing, contact with the
outside world, and a feeling about how
that contact feels. Plus, eleven--
whole rebirth experience. Plus, twelve--
living a whole life and then dying again.
Those are going to finish in the third life.
Therefore we can say that it is possible
that it can take three lives for one set
of twelve, but it may not be consecutive
wheels.
Then he gives a real example. And
there's a problem with the carving here
that I think should be read
differently. The yu de (YOD DE) I think
should be read yu do (YOD DO), which makes
more sense, and it's kind of important.
Okay. de yang per na (DE YANG DPER NA)--
let's take a real
example.
tse dir ngen song gi las...
(TSE 'DIR NGAN SONG GI LAS...)
...sag
(...BSAGS)--
in this lifetime you do some kind
of action towards another person which
is so bad you're going to become an animal,
or go to hell, or something like that.
le sag (LAS BSAGS) means that seed has been
injected into the mind. kyang (KYANG).
I'm glad I didn't
bet any money. chi kar ('CHI KHAR)--at the moment of
your death,
lama sog kyi ge sem la tsu
(BLA MA SOGS KYIS DGE SEMS LA BTZUD)
teacher, standing there, and they're like
"Try to think of something good! Try
to think of something good!" Then there's no
negative water, there's no negative fertilizer...
there's nothing to trigger the bad
karma at the moment that you die, because
your lama was standing there telling you
to have good thoughts.
And by the way, that's a very practical
reason why you should stay close to a
lama. People ask me, "Well, in the
modern world with the internet, then I
don't really have to stay physically
nearby my lama." But sometimes I get scared and I
think I should always stay near my lama,
because if I have a bad accident or
something, they can they can reach me in
ten or twenty minutes--that would be best, right?
Okay.
mir kye gyur gyi le shik la su tab
(MIR SKYE 'GYUR GYI LAS SHIG LA GSOS BTAB)--
because the lama was standing there and
giving good advice at the moment of the
selection of the karma for the next life,
they were born as a human instead of a
dog. So they're born as a human,
and of course they're going to die again,
but in this example they got angry in
the hospital at the last minute, and that
put water and fertilizer on this
negative seeds. And then the seed that was
collected in the first life got watered
in the second life, and then created the
third life in the lower realms.
de tsun ne (DES MTSON NAS)--So
just taking that one example, we can
understand
pen je dang drup je kyi bar du
('PHEN BYED DANG 'GRUB BYED KYI BAR DU)--
between the arrow shooting and the
factory producing a new life,
tse du me...
(TSE DU MAS...)
...chu
(...CHOD)--
there could be many intervening
lifetimes where nothing happens.
tendrel...
(RTEN 'BREL...)
...shen gyi tse yin pe drang du mi dren
(...GZHAN GYI TSE YIN PAS GRANGS SU MI 'DREN)--
now, let's say you did some really
bad karma in the first life, then in the
second life it didn't get water, and then
in the third life you got water at the
end of your life, and then it triggered a
new life. Is it four wheel parts? Is it
sections from four wheels? It's four
lifetimes. The answer is, by tradition, we
don't count this one. Why? Nothing
happened. Nothing happened with this
seed. I'll say it again. First life you
do something really bad--you plant a bad
seed, but it doesn't get watered by
negative
coffee meditation, for example. So in the
second life,
nothing happens with the seed--it's just
sitting in your mind. In the third life,
you feel happy about doing the
same bad thing. That happiness about bad
things in the third life puts water on
the bad seed from the first life, and
then the seed from the first life that
got watered in the third life creates a
bad rebirth in the fourth life. And by
tradition, in these Abhidharma teachings, when
we say "how many lifetimes did it take
the seed to do its thing," by tradition, we
only consider these three to be one set--
belong to the same set. So now I have
another question for Stanley. Hundred
dollars. If he wins, he's going to donate it to
the Mixed Nuts translations. Is it
possible to have more than three lives
in a single set? Yes or no?
[Stanley: In this tradition, no.]
Good, okay. Hundred dollars. I owe a hundred dollars to the Mixed Nuts.
Hopefully it'll be for refreshments,
because I'll be there. Okay, so now we're
going to wrap up.
dor na (MDOR NA) means okay "just
to summarize"
tendrel tsar chik gi wang du...
(RTEN 'BREL TSAR GCIG GI DBANG DU...)
tend outside check you on
...chepa
(...BYAS PA)--
if we restrict ourselves to one
set of dependence, or dependent
origination, which means one wheel,
yenlak nam nyur na tse nyi
(YAN LAG RNAMS MYUR NA TSE GNYIS)--
at the
fastest, it's going to take two lives.
yun ring...
(YUN RING...)
...na tse sum
(...NA TSE GSUM)--
at the slowest, it's going to
take three lives.
de le nyur gyang mi si
(DE LAS MYUR 'GYANG MI SRID)--
impossible to have less lives or more
lives. And I have an image here at the
end, which is many gears in a
watch. I'm going to get it up here for Stanley. There you go. So
this shows the inside of a watch. And
different gears are connecting with
different gears... they're all turning at the
same time. And it means every moment of
your life is interconnected with many
past lives and many future lives.
Then if you really understood these last
three or four classes, you should be
freaked out.
"Oh, Geshe-la, if a thousand wheels are spinning
at the same time, different
sets, what am I supposed to do?
What do you want me to do? How can I stop
it?
How can I get out of pain? How can I
reach Nirvana?"
The answer is marmahatha--
Strike
at the killing point. Where's the weak
point... I saw a movie the other
night ... I saw a TV show, oh yeah, Marco Polo,
=
00:24:34,130 --> 00:24:48,799
and there was a big fort. And it was a
very strong wall, very high, but they
found one place where the stones were
weak. And they attacked that place, and
the wall just fell down. So the wheel ... all
these thousands of wheels, they all
depend on one single point--it's
misunderstanding your life. It's the wife
in the kitchen saying, "I didn't do anything! He's yelling at me!" If you can
kill that one moment,
you kill all those wheels. It's amazing.
Twenty minutes, you can kill thousands of
wheels creating thousands of lifetimes.
Just see emptiness directly. And that's
where our author's going, and we'll hear
about it in the upcoming classes in this
series. See you tomorrow for session 20.
Thanks Stanley.